Guide to the David S. King Papers, 1963-1968
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
David S. King papers 1963-1968
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
King, David S.
0.2 Linear Feet 80 Items
David S King was a leader of the Massachusetts unit of the Southern Christian Leadership Conference (SCLC) during the 1960s. He was very active in the civil rights movement, and was arrested and sent to jail during a protest in Williamston, N.C. King was a chaplain at Amherst College and later became an Associate Pastor at the First Congregational Church. In addition, he founded the Laymen's Academy Oecuminical Studies (LAOS), which encouraged people to act upon their religious faith in their everyday lives and occupations.
Collection includes around 80 items, dated 1963 to 1968, that document events surrounding Rev. David S. King and his part in the civil rights movement. Items include letters to King while he was in jail and leading up to his arrest during a protest in Williamston, North Carolina in 1963. There are many letters and drawings from second and third graders at the Russell School in Pittsfield, Mass. Southern Christian Leadership Conference (SCLC) circular letters and press releases are present as well. In addition, there are numerous membership lists with contact information and clippings of articles about civil rights activities in Amherst, Mass. and Williamston, N.C. Other materials include a civil rights fact sheet, laws against housing discrimination, and a map of congressional districts in North Carolina.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The David S. King Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in December 2009.
Biographical Note
David S King was a leader of the Massachusetts unit of the Southern Christian Leadership Conference (SCLC) during the 1960s. He was very active in the civil rights movement, and was arrested and sent to jail during a protest in Williamston, N.C. King was a chaplain at Amherst College and later became an Associate Pastor at the First Congregational Church. In addition, he founded the Laymen's Academy Oecuminical Studies (LAOS), which encouraged people to act upon their religious faith in their everyday lives and occupations.
Collection Overview
Collection includes around 80 items, dated 1963 to 1968, that document events surrounding Rev. David S. King and his part in the civil rights movement. Items include letters to King while he was in jail and leading up to his arrest during a protest in Williamston, North Carolina in 1963. There are many letters and drawings from second and third graders at the Russell School in Pittsfield, Mass. Southern Christian Leadership Conference (SCLC) circular letters and press releases are present as well. In addition, there are numerous membership lists with contact information and clippings of articles about civil rights activities in Amherst, Mass. and Williamston, N.C. Other materials include a civil rights fact sheet, laws against housing discrimination, and a map of congressional districts in North Carolina.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Amherst (Mass.)--Race relations
Civil rights movements -- North Carolina
King, David S.
North Carolina -- Race relations
Russell School (Pittsfield, Mass.)
Southern Christian Leadership Conference
United States -- History -- 1961-1969
Williamston (N.C.)--Race relations
Description of Collection
- David S. King papers, 1963-1968, (1 box)
  - Personal correspondence, 1963-1968 and undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Letters sent to King in jail in Williamston, N.C.; discussion of civil rights issues; coordinating Williamston, N.C. protests; letter from Massachusetts Representative Silvio Conte.
  - Letters to King from the Russell School in Pittsfield, Mass., 1963 Nov.-Dec. (Folder 2)
    Letters sent to King in jail by second and third graders in Mrs. Purchase's class at the Russell School in Pittsfield, Mass. Some letters encourage King to continue his civil rights work while others comment on current events, especially the shooting of President Kennedy. Also included are several drawings by the students.
  - Circular letters, 1963-1969 (Folder 3)
    Letters encourage attendance at SCLC events, discuss protest plans and anti-Vietnam protest activities.
  - Meeting minutes, 1963-1965 (Folder 4)
    Mostly meeting minutes of the Human Relations Council of Amherst, Mass.
  - Articles, 1963-1965 (Folder 5)
    Clippings concerning the civil rights movement; conflict in Williamston, N.C.
  - Contact information and members lists (Folder 6)
    Information and membership lists for the fellowship of the committed and SCLC.
  - Church pamphlets, 1963-1965 (Folder 7)
  - Press releases, 1963-1964 (Folder 8)
    Press releases regarding Williamston, N.C. demonstrations and SCLC activities.
  - Miscellaneous, 1963-1965, undated (Folder 9)
    Civil rights fact sheet; laws against housing discrimination; map of North Carolina congressional districts; racial inequality bill, etc.